Guide to the John C. Almack Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John C. Almack papers
1920-1949
SC0047
Almack, John Conrad, 1883-1953.
11 Linear feet
ll linear feet
Manuscript and published articles and other writings by Almack, including articles for the American School Board Journal and the Stanford Spellers. Subjects include history, education, psychology, sociology, health, medicine, child growth and development, poetry, short story and mystery writing.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Lowell Turrentine, 1968.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Education at Stanford (1922-1949; emeritus, 1949-1953).
Description of the Collection
Manuscript and published articles and other writings by Almack, including articles for the American School Board Journal and the Stanford Spellers. Subjects include history, education, psychology, sociology, health, medicine, child growth and development, poetry, short story and mystery writing.
Access Terms
Almack, John Conrad, 1883-1953.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Children--Writing.; College teachers.; Education, Secondary.; English language--Orthography and spelling.; Graphology.; Manuscripts (literary).; Reprints.; School children--Health and hygiene.; United States--History
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - "A Clear Case Against Narcotics (For the Upper Grades)" by John C. Almack, Pacific Press Company, 1939 (Box 1)
  - "A History of the United States" by John C. Almack and Ephraim Adams, Harper and Brothers Publishers, 1931 (Box 1)
  - "A Key to Methods of Teaching" with topics selected by John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, undated (Box 1)
  - "A Key to School Administration" with topics selected by John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, undated (Box 1)
  - "A Survey of Mountain View High School" by John C. Almack, 1925 (Box 1)
  - "Administration and Personnel" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1935 (Box 1)
  - "The Administration of Consolidation and Villiage Schools" by John C. Almack and James F. Bursch, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1925 (Box 1)
  - "Administration of Personnel" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1935 (Box 2)
  - "The Administrative Provisions" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 2)
  - "Americanization - A Suggested Outline for Teachers of Aliens" by John C. Almack, 1919 August (Box 2)
  - "American School Administration" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 2)
  - "The Beginning Teacher" by John C. Almack and Albert R. Lang, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1928 (Box 3)
  - "Brief Survey of Chemwawa Indian School" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1937 (Box 3)
  - "California Ho!" by John C. Almack, undated (Box 3)
  - "Destiny in the Pacific, Part I" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 3)
  - "Destiny in the Pacific, Part II" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 3)
  - "The Development of the Building Program" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 4)
  - "Education for Citizenship" by John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1924 (Box 4)
  - "Education in Foreign Countries, Volume V" term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, undated (Box 4)
  - "Education 180" term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, 1937 (Box 4)
  - "Elementary Curriculum, Spelling" by John C. Almack and Harry F. Hedburg (manuscript), undated (Box 5)
  - "England" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 5)
  - "Facts First on Narcotics (For the Intermediate Grades) by John C. Almack, Pacific Press Publishing, 1939 (Box 5)
  - "Growth and Development of the Child, Volume I" a collection of term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, undated (Box 6)
  - "Growth and Development of the Child, Volume II" a collection of term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, undated (Box 6)
  - "Good Health with Joe and Jean, First Grade" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1941 (Box 7)
  - "Your Good Health, Second Grade" by John C. Almack and Pansy Jewett Abbott (manuscript), undated (Box 7)
  - "Everyday Health, Third Grade" by John C. Almack and Pansy Jewett Abbott (manuscript), undated (Box 7)
  - "Health at Home and at School, Fourth Grade" by John C. Almack and Helen B. Pryor (manuscript), undated (Box 7)
  - "Health at Work and Play, Fifth Grade" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1941 (Box 7)
  - "Natures Way to Health, Sixth Grade" by John C. Almack and Helen B. Pryor (manuscript), 1941 (Box 7)
  - "Progress in Health Sciences, Seventh Grade" by John C. Almack and Helen B. Pryor (manuscript), undated (Box 8)
  - "Healthful Living, Eight Grade" by John C. Almack and Helen B. Pryor (manuscript), undated (Box 8)
  - "The History of an Educational Movement" a collection of term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, undated (Box 8)
  - "History of Education Chart" by Lester B. Sands and John C. Almack, Stanford University Press, 1939 (Box 8)
  - "History of Oregon Normal School" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 8)
  - "History of the United States, Part I" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 9)
  - "History of the United States, Part II" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 9)
  - "History of the United States, Part III" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 9)
  - "History of the United States, Part IV" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 9)
  - "Homes - Old and New" by John C. Almack, 1935 (Box 10)
  - "The Hygiene of the School Child" by Lewis M. Terman and John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1929 (Box 10)
  - "Influenza - Enigma of Science" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 10)
  - "The John C. Almack Dinner" printed program of dinner given to honor Professor Alamck by Phi Delta Kappa, undated (Box 10)
  - "Leisure, Loafing or Living? A Historical Sketch of the Leisure Objective in Education" by John C. Almack, 1935 May (Box 10)
  - "The Library in Education" a collection of term papers for and edited by John C. Almack, 1936 (Box 11)
  - "Life and Health" by Charles C. Wilson, John L. Bracken, and John C. Almack, the Bobbs-Merril Company, 1945 (Box 11)
  - "The Literature and Problems of School Buildings, I" by John C. Almack, 1925 (Box 11)
  - "The Literature and Problems of School Buildings, II" by John C. Almack, 1925 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and post cards, undated (Box 11)
  - "Memory Book" presented to John C. Almack from his friends and Phi Delta Kappa, 1949 (Box 11)
  - "Modern School Administration - Its Problems and Progress" edited by John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1933 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, First Book" by John C. Almack, Lillian E. Billington, Elmer H. Staffelbach and John Powers, Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Second Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Third Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Fourth Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Fifth Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Sixth Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Seventh Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Eighth Book" by John C. Almack et. al., Laurel Book Company, 1948 (Box 12)
  - "New Laurel Handwriting, Teachers Manual", 1948 (Box 12)
  - "Oregon - Yesterday and Today" by John C. Almack and Don Nugent (manuscript), 1930 (Box 12)
  - "Efficiency of Mental Work by Consulting Pairs" by John C. Almack and James F. Bursch published in The American Journal of Sociology, 1930 March (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "The Problem of Teacher Tenure" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1921 November (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Making the Salary Schedule" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1938 April (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Making the Salary Schedule" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1938 May (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Civil Liberties: A War-Time Problem of the Schools" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1944 June (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Better Lighting for Better Seeing Part I" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1950 May (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "Better Lighting for Better Seeing Part II" by John C. Almack published in The American School Board Journal, 1950 July (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Education for Adequate School Support" by John C. Almack published in The Annals, 1935 November (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "A New Approach to the Health Curriculum" by John C. Almack published in California Journal of Elementary Education, 1934 November (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "The Issue in Teacher Training" by John C. Almack published in Educational Administration and Supervision, 1925 April (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "Scientific Method in Teaching" by John C. Almack published in Educational Method, 1933 March (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "Reading for Professional Advancement" by John C. Almack published in Educational Progress, 1927 May (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "Teaching Oral and Written Language" by John C. Almack published in Educational Progress, 1928 March (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - "Related Factors in Spelling Method" by John C. Almack and E. H. Staffelback published in The Elementary School Journal, 1933 December (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - "The Human Side of George Washington" by John C. Almack published in Hawaii Educational Review, 1932 February (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - "Helping the Child Face War" by John C. Almack published in Health, 1942 November (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "Is Your Child a Bundle of Nerves" by John C. Almack published in Health, 1942 December (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "Educating the Nervous Child" by John C. Almack published in Health, 1943 January (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - "How France Trains for Citizenship" by John C. Almack and Ruth Bormose published in The Historical Outlook, 1925 October (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "The Shibboleth of the Frontier" by John C. Almack published in The Historical Outlook, 1925 May (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - "A Symposium on the Classification of Educational Research" by John C. Almack et. al published in Journal of Educational Research, 1931 May (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - "A Symposium on the Classification of Educational Research" by John C. Almack et. al published in Journal of Educational Research, 1931 June (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - "The Principle of the Nomograph in Education" by John C. Almack and William G. Carr reprinted in Journal of Educational Research, 1926 December (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - "An Experimental Study of Individual Improvement in Spelling" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach reprinted in Journal of Educational Research, 1935 September (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - "A Specific Program for the High School Curriculum" by John C. Almack published in Listen, 1952 September - December (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - "Aspects of the Tenure Problem" by John C. Almack published in Los Angeles School Journal, 1930 November 17 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - "Giving the Gifted a Chance" and "A Test in English Composition - Writing the Friendly Letter" by John C. Almack published in Oregon Teachers Monthly, 1918 December (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - "History of Oregon Normal Schools" by John C. Almack published in The Quarterly of the Oregon Historical Society, 1920 June (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - "Educational Research and Statistics: The Course in Civics for Junior High School" by John C. Almack published in School and Society, 1920 December 18 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - "The Influence of Intelligence on the Selection of Associates" by John C. Almack published in School and Society, 1922 November 4 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - "Historical Decelopment of School Administration" by John C. Almack published in School and Society, 1936 May 9 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - "The Method of Applied Science in Teaching and Administration" by John C. Almack published in School and Society, 1938 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - "Universities - Old and New" by John C. Almack published in School and Society, 1939 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - "Poems" Volumes I and II by John C. Almack, 1932 (Box 15)
  - "Poems of Inexperience" by John C. Almack, undated (Box 15)
  - "The Poet's Wife and Other Stories" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1932 (Box 15)
  - "Problems of the Teaching Profession" by John C. Almack and Albert R. Lang, Houghton-Mifflin Company (Box 15)
  - "Proposed System of Junior Colleges for the State of California" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1937 (Box 15)
  - "The Red Dagger (A Mystery Thriller)" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 16)
  - "Research and Thesis Writing" by John C. Almack, Houghton-Mifflin Company, 1930 (Box 16)
  - "Roads to Reading" by Reba J. Mack, William A. McCall and John C. Almack, Harcourt Brace and Company, 1937 (Box 16)
    Includes an Answer Book and a Student Record Book
  - "Salt of the Earth" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 16)
  - "The School Board Member" by John C. Almack, The MacMillan Company, 1933 (Box 16)
  - "Report of the Senate Interim Committee on Education" California Legislature with John C. Almack as consultant (manuscript), 1949 (Box 17)
  - "Reports of the California Senate's Investigating Committee on Education" 5th, 6th and 7th reports with John C. Almack as consultant, 1949 (Box 17)
  - "First Report of the Senate Investigating Committee on Education" Sen. Nelson S. Dilsworth, et. al., with John Almack as consultant, undated (Box 17)
  - "Sense of Humor Test" designed by John C. Almack, undated (Box 17)
  - "Skohby: the Snow Dog" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 17)
  - "Stanford Report on School Reorganization in California" by John C. Almack (manuscript), 1938 (Box 17)
  - "The Story of Knighthood" by John C. Almack, 1935 (Box 18)
  - "Survey of the Monterey Union High School" by the Division of School House Planning, Department of Education, State of California and by John C. Almack and Harold R. Benjamin, undated (Box 18)
  - "Teacher's Salaries" by John C. Almack (manuscript), undated (Box 18)
  - "Track of the Sun" by John C. Almack, The Metropolitan Press, 1937 (Box 18)
  - "Washington and the Constitution, Grades Nine to Twelve" by John C. Almack, Johnson Publishing Company, 1931 (Box 18)
  - "Our Good Health, I (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson, Clara Belle Baker, Pansey Jewett Abbott and John C. Almack, the Bobbs-Merril Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "Healthy and Happy, II (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - "Everyday Health, III (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - "Health and Home, IV (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "Health at Work and Play, V (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - "Growing Healthfully, VI (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "Health Progress, VII (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - "Mordern Ways to Health, VIII (The American Health Series)" by Charles C. Wilson et. al., the Bobbs-Merrill Company, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Two" by John C. Almack, Elmer H. Staffelbach, and Wayman J. Williams, Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Three" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Four" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Five" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Six" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Seven" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - "The New Stanford Speller, Grade Eight" by John C. Almack, et. al., Laidlow Brothers, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Teachers Manual and Answer Book for the New Stanford Speller, Grades 2 and 3, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Teachers Manual and Answer Book for the New Stanford Speller, Grades 4, 5 and 6, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Teachers Manual and Answer Book for the New Stanford Speller, Grades 7 and 8, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Two" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Three" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Four" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Five" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Seven" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - "The Stanford Speller, Grade Eight" by John C. Almack and Elmer H. Staffelbach, Laidlow Brothers, 1929 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Memory volume: Letters on his retirement from colleagues and former students, 1949, and a few on his death in 1954, 1949, 1954 (Box 22)
  - Memory volume: Other correspondence and clippings, 1930-1955 (Box 22)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2006-112
  - "Influenza: 'The Malady Enigmatique'" written with Helen B. Pryor, 1940 (typescipt) (Box 1)
  - "Salt of the Earth" undated (typescript novel) (Box 1)